last time we have seen that a matrix can
be written basically let me draw here
the matrix so we had similar roles right
and then we multiplied usually design by
one one column all right and so whenever
we multiply these guys you can see these
and as two types two different
equivalent types of representation it
can you see right you don't is it
legible okay so you can see basically as
the output of this product has been a
sequence of like the first row times
this column vector and then again I'm
just okay shrinking them this should be
the same size right right because
otherwise you can't multiply them so you
have this one and so on right until the
last one and this is gonna be my final
vector and we have seen that each of
these bodies here what are these I talk
to me please
there's a scalar products right but what
do they represent what is it how can we
call it what's another name for calling
a scalar product I show you last time a
demonstration with some Chi government
trigonometry right what is it
so this is all the projection if you
talk about geometry or you can think
about this as a nun normalized cosine
value right so this one is going to be
my projection basically of one kernel or
my input signal onto the kernel right so
these are projections projection alright
and so then there was also a another
interpretation of this like there is
another way of seeing this which was
what basically we had the first column
of the matrix a multiplied by the first
element of the X of these of this vector
right so back element number one then
you had a second call
time's the second element of the X
vector until you get to the last column
right times the last an element right
suppose that this is long N and this is
M times n right so the height again is
going to be the dimension towards we
should - and the width of a matrix is
dimension where we're coming from
second part was the following so we said
instead of using this matrix here
instead since we are doing convolutions
because we'd like to exploit sparsity a
stationarity and compositionality of the
data we still use the same matrix here
perhaps right we use the same guy here
but then those kernels we are going to
be using them over and over again the
same current across the whole signal
right so in this case the width of this
matrix is no longer be it's no longer n
as it was here is going to be K which is
gonna be the kernel size right so here
I'm gonna be drawing my thinner matrix
and this one is gonna be K lowercase K
and the height maybe we can still call
it n okay all right so let's say here I
have several kernels for example let me
have my tsiyon carnal then I may have my
other non green let me change
let's put pink so you have this one and
then you may have green one right and so
on so how do we use these kernels right
now so we basically can use these
kernels by stacking them and shifted
them a little bit right so we get the
first kernel out of here and then you're
gonna get basically you get the first
guy here then you shift it shift it
shift it and so on right until you get
the whole matrix and we were putting a 0
here and a 0 here right this is just
recap and then you have this one for the
blue color now you do magic here and
just do copy copy and I you do paste
and now you can also do color see
fantastic magic and we have pink one and
then you have the last one right can I
do the same copy yes I can do fantastic
so you cannot do copy and paste on the
paper
all right color and the last one light
green okay all right so we just
duplicate how many matrices do we have
now how many layers no don't count the
number like there are letters on the on
the screen and K or M what is it what is
K the side usually you're just guessing
you shouldn't be guessing you should
tell me the correct answer I think about
this as a job interview I'm training you
so how many maps we have and right so
this one here are as many as my M which
is the number of rows of this initial
thing over here right all right so what
is instead the width of this little
kernel here okay right okay what is the
height of this matrix what is the height
of the matrix
you sure
try again
I can't hear and minus k plus one okay
and the final what is the output of this
thing right so the output is going to be
one vector which is gonna be of height
the same right and minus k plus 1 and
then it should be correct yeah but then
how many what is the thickness of this
final vector M right so this stuff here
and goes as thick as M right so this is
where we left last time right but then
someone asked me now then I realized so
we have here as many as the different
colors right so for example in this case
if I just draw to make sure we
understand what's going on you have the
first thing here now you have the second
one here and I have the third one right
in this case all right so last time they
asked me if someone asked me at the end
of the class so how do we do convolution
when we end up in this situation over
here because here we assume that my
corners are just you know whatever K
long let's say three long but then they
are just one little vector right and so
somebody told me no then what do you do
from here like how do we keep going
because now we have a thickness before
we started with a something here this
vector which had just n elements right
are you following so far I'm going
faster because we already seen these
things I'm just reviewing but are you
with me until now yes no yes okay
fantastic so let's see how we actually
keep going so the thing is
show you right now is actually assuming
that we start with that long vector
which was of height what was the height
and right but in this case also this one
means that we have something that looks
like this and so you have basically here
this is 1 this is also 1 so we only have
a monophonic signal for example and this
was n the height right all right so
let's assume now we're using a
stereophonic system so what is gonna be
my domain here so you know my X can be
thought as a function that goes from the
domain to the are number of channels so
what is this guy here yeah x is one
dimension and somewhere so what is this
Omega we have seen this slide last slide
of Tuesday lesson right second Omega is
not set of real numbers no someone else
tries we are using computers it's time
line yes and how many samples you you
have one sample number sample number two
or sample number three so you have
basically a subset of the natural space
right so this one is going to be
something like 0 1 2 so on set which is
gonna be subset of n right so it's not
our R is gonna be if you have time
continuous domain what you see in this
case the in the case I just showed you
so far what is seen in this case now
number of input channels because this is
going to be my X right this is my input
so in this case we show so far in this
case here we were just using one so it
means we have a monophonic audio let's
seven now the assumption make the
assumption that this guy is that it's
gonna be two such that you're gonna be
talking about stereo phonic signal right
okay
so let's see how this stuff changes so
in this case my let me think yeah so how
do I draw I'm gonna just draw right
little complain if you don't follow
are you following so far yes because if
i watch my tablet I don't see you right
so you should be complaining if
something doesn't make sense right
otherwise becomes boring from waiting
and watching you all the time
right yes no yes okay I'm boring okay
thank you
all right so we have here this signal
right and then now we have some
thickness in this case what is the
thickness of this guy see right so in
this case this one is going to be C and
in the case of the stereophonic signal
you're gonna just have two channels left
and right and this one keeps going down
right all right so our kernels if I'd
like to perform a convolution over this
signal right so you have different same
pussy right and so on right if I'd like
to perform a convolution one big
convolution I'm not talking about two
deconvolution right because they are
still using domain which is here number
one right so this is actually important
so if I ask you what type of signal this
is you're gonna be basically
you have to look at this number over
here right so we are talking about one
dimensional signal which is one
dimensional domain right 1d domain okay
so we are still using a 1d signal but in
this case it has you know you have two
values per point so what kind of kernels
are we gonna be using so I'm gonna just
draw it in this case we're gonna be
using something similar like this so I'm
gonna be drawing this guy let's say I
have K here which is gonna be my width
of the kernel but in this case I'm gonna
be also have some thickness in this case
here right so basically you apply this
thing here okay and then you can go
second line and third line and so on
right so you may still have like here m
kernels but in this case you also have
some thickness which has to match the
other thickness right so this thickness
here has to match the thickness of the
input size so let me show you how to
apply the convolution so you're gonna
get one of these slices here and then
you're gonna be applying this over here
okay and then you simply go down this
way
alright so whenever you apply these you
perform this guy here the inner product
with these over here what you get it's
actually a one by one is a scalar so
whenever I use this orange thingy here
on the left hand side and I do a dot
product scalar product with this one I
just get a scalar so this is actually my
convolution in 1d the convolution in 1d
means that it goes down this way and
only in one way that's why it's called
1d but we multiply each element of this
mask times this guy here now a second
row and this guy here okay
you saw you multiply all of them you sum
all of them and then you get your first
output here okay so whenever I make this
multiplication I get my first output
here then I keep sliding this kernel
down and then you're gonna get the
second output third out fourth and so on
until you go down at the end then what
happens then happens that I'm gonna be
picking up different kernel I'm gonna
back it let's say I get the third one
okay let's get the second one I get a
second one and I perform the same
operation you're gonna get here this one
actually let's actually make it like a
matrix
you go down okay until you go with the
last one which is gonna be the end right
the empty kernel which is gonna be going
down this way you get the last one here
okay yes no confusing clearing so this
was the question I got at the end of the
class yeah Suzy yeah because it's a dot
product of all those values between so
basically do the projection of this part
of the signal onto this kernel so you'd
like to see what is the contribution
like what is the alignment of this part
of the signal on to this specific
subspace okay this is how a convolution
works when you have multiple channels so
far I'll show you just with single
channel now we have multiple channels
okay so oh yeah yeah in one second one
and one one at the top one at the bottom
so you actually lose the first row here
and you lose the last row here so at the
end in this case the output is going to
be n minus three plus one so you lose
two one on top okay in this case you
lose two at the bottom if you actually
do a Center at the center the
convolution usually you lose one at the
beginning one at the end every time you
perform a convolution you lose the
number of the dimension of the kernel
minus one you can try if you put your
hand like this you have a kernel of
three you get the first one here and it
is matching then you switch one and then
you switch to right so okay with fight
let's tell a parent of two right so you
have your signal of five you have your
kernel with two you have one two three
and four so we started with five and you
end up with four because you use a
kernel size of two if you use a kernel
size of three you get one two and three
so you goes to if you use a kernel size
of three okay
so you can always try to do this
alright so I'm gonna show you now the
dimensions of these kernels and the
outputs with PI torch okay Yes No
all right good okay mister can you see
anything
yes right I mean zoom a little bit more
okay so now we can go we do conv
activate activate and then we have
debate yeah PDL right pythor sleep
learning so here we can just run ipython
if i press ctrl L I clear the screen and
we can do import torch then I can do
from torch import nn so now we can see
for example called let's set my
convolutional convolutional layer it's
going to be equal to NN conf
and then I can keep going until I get
this one let's say yeah let's say I have
no idea how to use this function I just
put a question mark I press ENTER and
I'm gonna see here now the documentation
okay so in this case you're gonna have
the first item is going to be the input
channel then I have the output channels
then I have the corner sighs alright so
for example we are going to be putting
here input channels we have a stereo
signal so we put two channels the number
of corners we said that was M and let's
say we have 16 kernels so this is the
number of kernels I'm gonna be using and
then let's have our kernel size of what
the same I use here so let's have K or
the kernel size equal 3 okay in so here
I'm going to define my first convolution
object so if I print this one comes
you're gonna see we have a convolution a
2d combo sorry 1 deconvolution made that
okay so we have a 1d convolution
which is going from two channels so a
stereophonic to a sixteen channels means
I use sixteen kernels the skirmish size
is 3 and then the stride is also 1 ok so
in this case I'm gonna be checking what
is gonna be my convolutional weights
what is the size of the weights
how many weights do we have how many how
many planes do we have for the weights
16 right so we have 16 weights what is
the length of the the day of the key of
D of the kernel okay Oh what is this -
Janis right so I have 16 of these
scanners which have thickness - and then
length of 3 ok makes sense right because
you're gonna be applying each of these
16 across the whole signal so let's have
my signal now you're gonna be is gonna
be equal toage dot R and and and oh
sighs I don't know let's say 64 I also
have to say I have a batch of size 1 so
I have a virtual site one so I just have
one signal and then this is gonna be 64
how many channels we said this has two
right so I have one signal one example
which has two channels and has 64
samples so this is my X hold on what is
the convolutional bias size
a 16 right because you have one bias /
plain / / / way ok so what's gonna be in
our my convolution of X the output hello
so I'm gonna still have one sample right
how many channels 16 what is gonna be
the length of the signal okay that's
good 6 fix it okay fantastic
all right so what if I'm gonna be using
a convolution with size of the kernel 5
what do I get now yet to shout I can't
hear you
60 okay you're following fantastic okay
so let's try now instead to use a hyper
spectral image with a 2d convolution
okay so I'm going to be coding now my
convolution here is going to be my in
this case is correct or is going to be a
conf come to D again I don't know how to
use it so I put a question mark and then
I have here input channel output channel
criticize strident padding okay so I'm
going to be putting inputs tried input
channel so it's a hyper spectral image
with 20 planes so what's gonna be the
input in this case 20 right because you
have you start from 20 spectral bands
then we're gonna be inputting the output
number of channels we let's say we're
gonna be using again 16 in this case I'm
going to be inputting the kernel size
since I'm planning to use okay let's
actually define let's actually define my
signal first so my X is gonna be a torch
dot R and and let's say one sample with
20 channels of height for example I
guess 6128 well hold on 64 and then with
128 okay so this is gonna be my my input
my eople data okay
so my convolution now it can be
something like this so I have 20
channels from input 16 our Mike Ernest
I'm gonna be using then I'm gonna be
specifying the kernel size in this case
let's use something that is like three
times five okay so what is going to be
the output what are the kernel size
anyone yes no what no 20 Janice is the
channels of the input data right so you
have how many kernels here 16 right
there you go
we have 16 kernels which have 20
channels such that they can lay over the
input 3 by 5 right teeny like a short
like yeah short but large ok so what is
gonna be my convolution on eggs sized
one 1660 224 let's say I'd like to
actually add back the I'd like to head
the sing dimensionality I can add some
padding right so here there is going to
be the stride I'm gonna have a stride of
1 again if you don't remember the the
syntax you can just put the question
mark can you figure out and then how
much strive should I add now how much
stride in the y-direction sorry yes how
much padding should I add in the
y-direction one because it's gonna be
one on top one on the bottom but then
then on the x-direction okay you know
you're following fantastic and so now if
I just run this one you wanna get the
initial size okay so now you have both
1d and 2d the point is that what is the
dimension of a convolutional kernel and
symbol for to the dimensional signal
again I repeat what is the
dimensionality of the collection of
careness use for two-dimensional data
again for right so four is gonna be the
number of dimensions that are required
to store the collection of kernels when
you perform 2d convolutions the one is
going to be the stride so if you don't
know how this works you just put a
question mark and gonna tell you here so
stride is gonna be telling you you
stride off you move every time the
kernel by one if you are the first one
means you only is the batch size so
torch expects you to always use batches
meaning how many signals you're using
just one right so that our expectation
if you send an input vector which is
going to be input tensor which has
dimension three is gonna be breaking and
complain okay so we have still some time
to go in the second part all right
second part is going to be so you've
been computing some derivatives right
for the first homework right so the
following homework maybe you have to do
you have to compute this one okay you're
supposed to be laughing it's a joke okay
there you go
fantastic so this is what you can wrote
back in the 90s for the computation of
the gradients of the of the lsdm which
are gonna be covered I guess in next
next lesson so how somehow so they had
to still do these things right it's kind
of crazy nevertheless we can use Python
to have automatic computation of these
gradients so we can go and check out how
these automatic gradient works
okay all right so
all right so we are going to be going
now to the notebook number three which
is the yeah
invisible let me see if I can highlight
it now it's even worse okay number three
Auto gratitute Oriole okay let me go
fullscreen
okay so out of our tutorial was gonna be
here here just create my tensor which
has as well these required gradients
equal true in this case I mean asking
torch please track all the gradient
computations did it got the competition
over the tensor such that we can perform
computation of partial derivatives okay
in this case I'm gonna have my Y is
going to be so X is simply gonna be one
two three four the Y is going to be X
subtracted number two okay alright so
now we can notice that there is this
grad F n grad f NN FN function here so
let's see what this stuff is we go sit
there and see oh this is a sub backward
what is it meaning that the Y has been
generated by a module which performs the
subtraction between X and and - right so
you have X minus 2 therefore if you
check who generated Y well there's a sub
a subtraction module ok so what's gonna
be now the God function of X you're
supposed to answer oh okay
why is none
because they should have written there
Alfredo generated that right okay all
right none is fine as well
okay so let's actually put our nose
inside we were here we can actually
access the first element you have the
accumulation why is the accumulation I
don't know I forgot but then if you go
inside there you're gonna see the
initial vector the initial tensor we are
using is the one two three four okay so
inside this computational graph you can
also find the original tensor okay all
right so let's now get the Z and inside
is gonna be my Y square times three and
then I compute my average a it's gonna
be the mean of Z right so if I compute
the square of this thing here and I
multiply by three and I take the average
so this is the square part times 3 and
then this is the average okay so you can
try if you don't believe me all right so
let's see how this thing looks like so
I'm gonna be promoting here all these
sequence of computations so we started
by from a two by two matrix what was
this guy here to buy - who is this X
okay you're following it cool then we
subtracted - right and then we
multiplied by Y twice right that's why
you have to ro so you get the same
subtraction that is the whyatt
the X minus 2 multiplied by itself then
you have another multiplication what is
this okay multiply by three and then you
have the final the mean backward because
this Y is green because it's mean no
okay yeah thank you for laughing okay so
I compute back prop right
what does backdrop do what does this
line do
I want to hear everyone you know already
we compute what radians right so black
propagation is how you compute the
gradients how do we train your networks
with gradients ain't right
or whatever Aaron said yesterday back
propagation is that is used for
computing the gradient completely
different things okay
please keep them separate don't merge
them everyone after a bit that don't
they don't see me those two things keep
colliding into one mushy thought don't
it's painful okay she'll compute the
gradients right so guess what we are
computing some gradients now okay so we
go on your page it's going to be what
what was a it was the average right so
this is 1/4 right the summation of all
those red eyes okay
what so I goes from 1 to 4
okay so what is that I said I is going
to be equal to 3y I square right yeah no
questions no okay all right and then
this one is was equal to 3 times X minus
2 square right so a what does it belong
to
where does a belong to what is the R
right so it's a scaler
okay all right so now we can compute da
over DX so how much is this stuff you're
gonna have 1/4 comes out forum here and
then you have you know let's have this
one with respect to the X ice element
okay so we're gonna have this one I
inside is that I have the three why I
Square and it's gonna be three X minus
two square right so these three comes
out here the two comes down as well and
then you multiply by X I minus 2 right
so far should be correct okay fantastic
all right so my X was this element here
actually let me compute as well this one
so this one goes away this one becomes
true this is 1.5 times X I minus 3 right
- 2 - 3
ok mathematics okay okay thank you
all right so what's gonna be my da over
the X I'm actually writing the transpose
directly here so for the first element
you have one you have one times 1.5 so
1.5 minus 3 you get 1 minus 1.5 right
second one is going to be 3 minus 3 you
get 0 Ryan this is 3 minus 3
maybe I should write everything right so
you're actually following so you have
1.5 minus 3 now you have 3 minus 3 below
you have 4 point 5 minus 3 and then the
last one is going to be 6 minus 3 which
is going to be equal to minus 1 point 5
0 1 point 5 and then 3 right you agree
ok let me just write this on here
okay just remember so we have you be
computed the backpropagation here I'm
gonna just bring it to the gradients and
then the right it's the same stuff we
got here right such that I don't have to
transpose it here whenever you perform
the partial derivative in PI tours you
get the same the same shape is the input
dimension so if you have a weight
whatever dimension then when you compute
the partial you still have the same
dimension they don't swap they don't
turn okay they just use this for
practicality at the correct version I
mean the the gradient should be the
transpose of that thing sorry did
Jacobian which is the transpose of the
gradient right if it's a vector but this
is a tensor so whatever we just used the
same same shape thing no so this one
should be a flipping I believe maybe I'm
wrong but I don't think all right so
this is like basic these basic PI tours
now you can do crazy stuff because we
like crazy right
I mean I do I think if you like me you
like crazy
right okay so here I just create my
vector X which is going to be a three
dimensional well a one-dimensional
tensor of three items I'm going to be
multiplying X by two then I call this
one Y then I start my counter to zero
and then until the norm of the Y is long
thousand below thousand I keep doubling
Y okay and so you can get like a dynamic
graph right the graph is base is
conditional to the actual random
initialization which you can't even tell
because I didn't even use a seed so
everyone that is running this stuff is
gonna get different numbers so these are
the
final values of the why can you tell me
how many iterations we run so the mean
of this stuff is actually lower than a
thousand yeah but then I'm asking
whether you know how many times this
loop went through no good why it's
random Rises you know it's bad question
about bad questions next time I have a
something for you okay so I'm gonna be
printing this one now I'm telling you
the grabbed are 2048 right
just check the central one for the
moment right this is the actual gradient
so can you tell me now how many times
the loop went on so someone said 11 how
many ends up for 11 okay for people just
roast their hands what about the others
okay any other guys 11 10
okay we have actually someone that has
the right solution and this loop went on
for 10 times why is that because you
have the first multiplication by 2 here
and then loop goes on over and over and
multiplies by 2 right so the final
number is gonna be the least number of
iterations in the loop plus the
additional like addition and
multiplication outside right yes no
you're sleeping maybe okay I told you
not to eat before class otherwise you
get groggy okay so inference this is
cool so here I'm gonna be just having
both my X & Y we are gonna just do
linear regression right linear or
whatever think the add operator is just
the scalar product okay so both the X
and W has
have the requires gradient equal to true
being this means we are going to be
keeping track of the the gradients and
the computational graph so if I execute
this one you're gonna get the partial
derivatives of the inner product with
respect to the Z with respect to the
input is gonna be the weights right so
in the range is the input right and the
ones are the weights so partial
derivative with respect to the input is
gonna be the weights partial with
respect to the weights are gonna be the
input right yes no yes okay now I just
you know usually it's this one is the
case I just have required gradients for
my parameters because I'm gonna be using
the gradients for updating later on the
the parameters of the mother is so in
this case you get none let's have in
this case instead what I usually do
wanna do inference when I do inference I
tell torch a torch stop tracking any
kind of operation so I say torch no God
please so this one regardless of whether
your input always have the required
grass true or false whatever when I say
torch no brats you do not have any
computation a graph taken care of right
therefore if I try to run back
propagation on a tensor which was
generated from like doesn't have
actually you know graph because this one
doesn't have a graph you're gonna get an
error okay so if I run this one you get
an error and you have a very angry face
here because it's an error and then it
takes your element 0 of tensor does not
require grads and does not have a god
function right so II which was the yeah
whatever they reside here actually then
you couldn't run back problems that
because there is no graph attached to
that ok questions this is so powerful
you cannot do it this time with tensor
you okay tensor flow is like whatever
yeah more stuff here actually more stuff
coming right now
[Applause]
so we go back here we have inside the
extra folder he has some nice cute
things I wanted to cover both of them
just that we go just for the second I
think sorry the second one is gonna be
the following so in this case we are
going to be generating our own specific
modules so I like let's say I'd like to
define my own function which is super
special amazing function I can decide if
I want to use it for you know training
Nets I need to get the forward pass and
also have to know what is the partial
derivative of the input respect to the
output such that I can use this module
in any kind of you know point in my
inner code such that you know by using
back prop you know chain rule you just
plug the thing no young went on several
times as long as you know partial
derivative of the output with respect to
the input you can plug these things
anywhere in your chain of operations so
in this case we define my addition which
is performing the addition of the two
inputs in this case but then when you
perform the back propagation if you have
an addition what is the back propagation
so if you have a addition of the two
things you get an output when you send
down the gradients what does it happen
with the with the gradient it gets you
know copied over both sides right and
that's why you get both of them are
copies or the same thing and they are
sent through one side of the other you
can execute this stuff you're gonna see
here you get the same gradient both ways
in this case I have a split so I come
from the same thing and then I split and
I have those two things doing something
else if I go down with the gradient what
do I do you add them right and that's
why we have here the add install you can
execute this one you're going to see
here that we had these two initial
gradients here and then when you went up
or sorry when you went down the two
things the two gradients sum together
and they are here okay
so again if you use pre-made things in a
PI torch they are correct this one you
can mess around you can put any kind of
different in
for a function and backward function I
think we ran out of time other questions
before we actually leave no all right so
I see on Monday and stay warm but